Finding Aid for the Frederick Wightman Moore Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Frederick Wightman Moore Papers
1899-1909
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0299
0.84 linear_feet
Biography
Dr. Frederick Wightman Moore was born in East Lyme, Conn. October 18, 1863 to Mr. Ezra and Mrs. Juliette Moore. He earned his A.B in 1886 and his Ph.D. in 1890 from Yale. For two years after graduating, Dr. Moore traveled abroad pursuing his studies. During that time he spent three semesters at the University of Berlin. Between the years 1891 and 1892 Dr. Moore was a lecturer on sociology in the Wharton School of Finance of the University of Pennsylvania. In 1892 he came to Vanderbilt University as Adjunct Professor of History and Economics. From 1901 to 1908 he served as Professor of History and Economics, and Professor of History from 1909 to1911. In 1902 he became Editor of the Vanderbilt University Quarterly, and in 1904 he was awarded Dean of the Academic Department at Vanderbilt University. He held that position until the time of his death in 1911. Dr. Moore was a skilled writer, translator, and teacher. One of his most noted translations is, “Outlines of Sociology” by Dr. Ludwig Gumplowiez of the Imperial University, Gratz, Austria. A devout Christian, Dr. Moore became a member of the Immanuel Baptist Church in 1902 near the Vanderbilt campus. He was an active member in the Association of Colleges and Preparatory Schools of the Southern Schools serving as its Secretary and Treasurer in 1908. He was also a member of the American Historical Association, of the American Economical Association, and of the Tennessee Historical Association.
Scope and Content
The Frederick Wightman Moore Papers consist primarily of correspondence, research and lecture notes, and various writings from his career as Professor and Dean at Vanderbilt University. The collection contains 0.834 linear feet of materials. The correspondence, notes, and writings found in the collection provide a summary of Dr. Moore’s interests, specifically the teaching of History. Many of the letters are inquiries to other universities about the teaching of History in each respective school. There are also several speeches given as part of a lecture series discussing religion and sociology. The materials date roughly from 1899-1909, but approximately two-thirds of the writings from the collection are undated and have no attribution of authorship.
- Correspondence – Outgoing
  - March 23, 1903 – September 5, 1903, Three letters. March 23, 1903 to Mary A. Stevens; March 23, 1903 to John A. Brashear – Referred to Dr. Hunter who replied in holograph; September 5, 1903 to W.T. Scott with Scott’s reply written in holograph. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence - Incoming
  - Ames, Herman V. – Ballagh, J.C. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Banks, E.M. – Battle, Kemp P. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Boaman, Thor – Brown, Marshall S. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bulloch, Charles J. – Burnett, Edmund C. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Butler, James D. – Dickman, O.N. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dodd, William E. – Gray, John H. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hackett, Homer C. – Haskins, Charles H. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hatch, R. – Johnson, Allen (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Karnes, J.V.C. – Latane, John H. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Little, George T. – Millar, A.C. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Montague, W.L. – Riley, Franklin L. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Shurtleff, G.W. – Stanclift, Henry C. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Stephens, E.W. – Turner, E.K. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Turner, Frederick J. – Weston, Stephen F. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Mailing Lists
  - Mailing Lists (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Research / Lecture Notes
  - Notes on College Histories (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Economics Lecture Notes (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Economics Lecture Notes (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Economics Lecture Notes (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Economics Lecture Notes (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Economics Lecture Notes (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Economics Lecture Notes (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Economics Lecture Notes (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Economics Lecture Notes (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Notes on Conversations with Judge J.M. Dickinson, Morton B. Howell, and Dr. William J. Vaughn (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Writings
  - “A Contribution to the Political History of Louisiana” - Undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - “History of the Teaching of History” at University of Alabama, 1856 and South Carolina College, 1856. Related by Dr. William J. Vaughn, Saturday, January 10, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - “Judge John McCormick Lea – A Eulogy”, November 10, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - “The Period Before 1860 – A Sketch” from the Conference on the Study and Teaching of History in the South, American Historical Association, New Orleans, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Printed Circulars for Historical Research, March 20, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - “The Teaching of History in the University of Nashville” - Undated, “The Teaching of History in Vanderbilt University” – Undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Writings by Others
  - Speeches
    - “The Finality of The Christian Religion by George Burman Foster, Ph.D” A review read before The Old Oak Club, November 20, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - “The Fine Arts As Cultivated Accomplishments” Read before The Old Oak Club, November 25, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - “The Religious Aspects of Social Science” [Gay Lecture Series] Read before the faculty and students of the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary, April 3, 4, and 6, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - “The Sociological Concept” [Gay Lecture Series] – Undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - “The Sociological Function of The Ministry” [Gay Lecture Series] – Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Articles
    - “The Industrial Condition of Negroes in Nashville” – Undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - “Origin and Development of the Faust Legend” – Undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - “The Powers of the President” – Undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - “Recent American Diplomacy” – Undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - “Service for Others, A Social Law” – Undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - “Status of History in the University of Tennessee before 1860” by Lilian Wyckoff Johnson – October 10, 1903, includes 2 pages from the University of Tennessee Record Course Catalog (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - “The Teaching of History in American Colleges Previous to the Civil War” – Undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Untitled
    - [Andrew Jackson] – Undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - [English Educational Conditions] – Undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - [History of the Study of History] – Undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - [Race Population in the South] – Undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - [Sir Benjamin Thompson, Count of Rumford] – Undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - [Slavery] Notes compiled by Thomas D. McIntyre. See letter from Thomas D. McIntyre to Moore on July 11, 1895 - Folder 11 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - [United States History] – Undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Academic Career
  - Clippings and Invitations from American Historical Association Meeting, Providence, Rhode Island, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Research Notes (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Academic Department Paper (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Biographical
  - Printed biographical pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 56)